<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>VAWT | Mark Runacres</title>
    <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/tags/vawt/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://mrunacre.github.io/tags/vawt/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>VAWT</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://mrunacre.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>VAWT</title>
      <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/tags/vawt/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interaction of closely-spaced vertical-axis wind turbines</title>
      <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/project/vawt/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrunacre.github.io/project/vawt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Vertical-axis wind turbines, when placed close together, have an improved power
production and very interesting aerodynamics. The experimental side of this
project is the PhD project of Antoine Vergaerde. The computational side of the
project is taken care of by Greeshma Boohalli Shivamallegowda.
Both Antoine and Greeshma are supervised by

&lt;a href=&#34;https://flow.research.vub.be/en/tim-de-troyer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tim De Troyer&lt;/a&gt; and myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the viability of vertical-axis wind turbines for the production of
electricity is still open for debate, they may have certain niche applications,
and definitely have very interesting aerodynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We built our own set of scales models, shown above during a wind tunnel test run
at PoliMi in Italy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feasibility and performance assessment of small and medium-sized wind turbines</title>
      <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/publication/smwt_jochem/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrunacre.github.io/publication/smwt_jochem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is considerable uncertainty about the role that small and medium wind
turbines may play in the production of sustainable electricity. In the present
work, we identify the main factors affecting the economic viability of small and
medium wind turbines (herafter SMWTs). We then propose a framework for more
efficient and reliable predictions of the annual energy production of SMWTs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We
demonstrate that these turbines are indeed profitable, provided that an
appropriate turbine is selected and that the annual energy production is
estimated carefully. These seemingly simple tasks are non-trivial and current
practices too often lead to unreliable assessments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We first assemble a database of wind turbines with a rated power up to 100 kW.
Such a database is a necessary tool when assessing the feasibility of a project
involving SMWTs, since the market is very immature, with a wide variation in
quality between different turbines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then calculate the annual energy production (AEP) for a number of measurement
sites in Belgium and The Netherlands and for different independently-tested
SMWTs. Based on these data and on first principles, we show what the best
methods are to select an appropriate turbine and what the expected accuracy is
of the AEP estimate.
We have found that a particular statistical error has been overlooked in the
current methods to estimate the annual energy production. This error is the
possible mismatch of the averaging times with which wind speeds and turbine
power outputs are sampled. Using wind speed and power measurements, we show how
this error can be minimised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our findings have an immediate practical importance. We therefore apply our
methods in a number of case studies, and give recommendations for future SMWT
projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Experimental Characterization of VAWT Airfoils Under Turbulent Flows</title>
      <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/publication/d-22-a-7892-e-028444281-cbf-26-d-44-a-114-fd/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrunacre.github.io/publication/d-22-a-7892-e-028444281-cbf-26-d-44-a-114-fd/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effect of turbulence on the performance of VAWTs: An experimental study in two different wind tunnels</title>
      <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/publication/fc-241-dd-9-dfd-644-da-87295-df-737-fb-3-c-7-c/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrunacre.github.io/publication/fc-241-dd-9-dfd-644-da-87295-df-737-fb-3-c-7-c/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
