<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mark Runacres</title>
    <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://mrunacre.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Mark Runacres</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Mark Runacres</title>
      <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>High-fidelity surrogate wind data</title>
      <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/project/surrogate_data/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrunacre.github.io/project/surrogate_data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The objective of this project is to create a modelling framework for
high-fidelity surrogate wind data. This work is largely the PhD project of
Daniele D&amp;rsquo;Ambrosio whom I supervise with prof. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://flow.research.vub.be/en/tim-de-troyer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tim De Troyer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The increasing sophistication of wind turbine design and control generates a need for high-quality data. Therefore, the relatively limited set of measured wind data needs to be extended with computer-generated surrogate data, e.g. to make reliable statistical studies of energy production and mechanical loads. Surrogate data should realistically reflect the full scale of possible wind conditions. First, the surrogate data should conform to the same statistical descriptors as measured physical data (in particular the amplitude distribution and the frequency spectrum). There are methods that can handle this. A far bigger challenge is non-stationarity, reflected by the variation of wind conditions on distinct temporal scales (such as daily or seasonal variations). No existing method can fully capture this non-stationarity. Furthermore, wind data are three-dimensional, in the sense that information about the wind direction is as important as information about the wind speed.
In this application, we outline a unified mathematical framework to tackle the
twin challenges of non-stationarity and three- dimensionality. The framework
allows to generate non-stationary, three-dimensional wind time series with high
fidelity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a framework is generic and can be used to generate surrogate data for other
non-stationary processes, such as ocean waves or pollutant dispersion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A preprint of a paper outline the approach is available through 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.07218&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breathney: A modular design toolbox for an affordable ventilator with full functionality</title>
      <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/post/fablab/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrunacre.github.io/post/fablab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Covid-19 pandemic is still progressing globally and a small but significant
fraction of patients need mechanical ventilation at some point. Although some
countries have sufficient ventilators, there are indications of a future global
shortage of such devices. Medtronic released documents for their ventilator,
showing a global urgent need. Rapidly prototyped, industrially manufactured
ventilators can help alleviate this shortage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With crucial support from UZ Brussels , Flanders Make, Audi and other partners,
a team of 40 students, alumni, staff and external experts
at the Fablab Brussels have recently designed and prototyped
a ventilator
that has been produced industrially and is currently being tested extensively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We intend to contribute to the
world-wide ventilator effort in the following way:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perform the scientific experiments to investigate and iteratively increase the
level of compliance with published requirements (e.g.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://tinyurl.com/wfqtk4w&#34;&gt;https://tinyurl.com/wfqtk4w&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demonstrate that a fully functional ventilator can be mass-produced (&amp;gt;100
units daily for a mid-sized facility in e.g. automotive sector) with
minimal pressure on the medical supply chain, by maximally sourcing components
from non-medical sectors, at a well-documented unit cost that is affordable
compared to conventional ventilators (without being low-cost per se)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make available a toolbox for all aspects of ventilator system (mechanical,
electrical, sensors, control, interface). The different aspects are designed
in a modular manner so that e.g. the control unit can be used with both
pump-based and pneumatic approaches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the design open-source. Share the design and documentation. Assist other
groups worldwide in adapting design and setting up local production&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more at 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://breathney.vub.be&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the project&amp;rsquo;s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Design and manufacturing of a VAWT scale model</title>
      <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/publication/vawt_design/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrunacre.github.io/publication/vawt_design/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper describes the
design, manufacturing and validation of a vertical-axis wind turbine setup for
wind tunnel tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The potential of vertical-axis wind turbines (VAWTs) for specific applications
(floating off-shore or urban in- stallations) has been reconsidered in recent
years. This renewed interest has led to an increasing number of experimental
studies on VAWTs. A challenge of experimental work is correctly interpreting
experimental results but just as important is the design of the experimental
setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objective of the present study is to elaborate on the complete
development process of a VAWT wind tunnel test setup, from design to aerodynamic
interpretation. The effect of the design choices and structural characteristics
of the setup can be traced in the measured torque. The influence of structural
dynamics of an experimental setup are proven to influence unsteady measurements
significantly through the analysis of the spectral content of the measured
torque. An extensive modal analysis of the VAWT rotor allows to link modal
vibrations to their contaminating effect on the measured torque. In addition,
the dynamics of the sensors and setup are found to be important contributions to
the contamination of dynamic measurements. To interpret unsteady torque
measurements, the complete experimental setup needs to be dynamically
characterised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interaction of closely-spaced vertical-axis wind turbines</title>
      <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/project/vawt/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrunacre.github.io/project/vawt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Vertical-axis wind turbines, when placed close together, have an improved power
production and very interesting aerodynamics. The experimental side of this
project is the PhD project of Antoine Vergaerde. The computational side of the
project is taken care of by Greeshma Boohalli Shivamallegowda.
Both Antoine and Greeshma are supervised by

&lt;a href=&#34;https://flow.research.vub.be/en/tim-de-troyer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tim De Troyer&lt;/a&gt; and myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the viability of vertical-axis wind turbines for the production of
electricity is still open for debate, they may have certain niche applications,
and definitely have very interesting aerodynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We built our own set of scales models, shown above during a wind tunnel test run
at PoliMi in Italy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Experimental validation of the power enhancement of a pair of vertical-axis wind turbines</title>
      <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/publication/vawt_enhancement/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrunacre.github.io/publication/vawt_enhancement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Wind tunnel tests have been performed of individual and paired H-type Darrieus
vertical-axis wind turbines. The turbines in the paired configuration are
closely spaced, at 1.2 and 1.3 rotor diameters shaft to shaft, and are
counter-rotating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two directions of rotation were studied, one where the facing
(inner) blades move along with the incoming flow, and one where the facing
blades move against the wind. The wind tunnel tests confirm a net increase in
the power coefficient of the paired configuration compared with twice the power
coefficient of the individual turbine. We found average relative increases in
the power coefficients between 13% and 16%, which is consistent with numerical
studies available in the literature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distributed wind energy and small wind turbines.</title>
      <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/project/distributed_wind/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrunacre.github.io/project/distributed_wind/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been working on distributed wind energy since 2007. Jochem Vermeir&amp;rsquo;s PhD
thesis summarises a lot of the work that we did back then.
I was involved in IEA Wind Task 27 on Small wind turbines in strongly turbulent
environments and am currently involved in

&lt;a href=&#34;https://community.ieawind.org/task41/home&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;IEA Wind Task 41&lt;/a&gt; on distributed wind.
I am also a member of the Small Wind Technical Committee of the European Academy
for Wind Energy. Quentin Deltenre is close to finishing his PhD thesis on
&lt;em&gt;Sustainable retrofitting of high-rise rooftops&lt;/em&gt; in which rooftop-mounted small
wind turbines play a role.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feasibility and performance assessment of small and medium-sized wind turbines</title>
      <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/publication/smwt_jochem/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrunacre.github.io/publication/smwt_jochem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is considerable uncertainty about the role that small and medium wind
turbines may play in the production of sustainable electricity. In the present
work, we identify the main factors affecting the economic viability of small and
medium wind turbines (herafter SMWTs). We then propose a framework for more
efficient and reliable predictions of the annual energy production of SMWTs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We
demonstrate that these turbines are indeed profitable, provided that an
appropriate turbine is selected and that the annual energy production is
estimated carefully. These seemingly simple tasks are non-trivial and current
practices too often lead to unreliable assessments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We first assemble a database of wind turbines with a rated power up to 100 kW.
Such a database is a necessary tool when assessing the feasibility of a project
involving SMWTs, since the market is very immature, with a wide variation in
quality between different turbines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then calculate the annual energy production (AEP) for a number of measurement
sites in Belgium and The Netherlands and for different independently-tested
SMWTs. Based on these data and on first principles, we show what the best
methods are to select an appropriate turbine and what the expected accuracy is
of the AEP estimate.
We have found that a particular statistical error has been overlooked in the
current methods to estimate the annual energy production. This error is the
possible mismatch of the averaging times with which wind speeds and turbine
power outputs are sampled. Using wind speed and power measurements, we show how
this error can be minimised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our findings have an immediate practical importance. We therefore apply our
methods in a number of case studies, and give recommendations for future SMWT
projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An example preprint / working paper</title>
      <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/publication/preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrunacre.github.io/publication/preprint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo Academic&amp;rsquo;s Markdown slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code and math&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slides</title>
      <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/slides/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrunacre.github.io/slides/example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;create-slides-in-markdown-with-academic&#34;&gt;Create slides in Markdown with Academic&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Academic&lt;/a&gt; | 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/managing-content/#create-slides&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efficiently write slides in Markdown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3-in-1: Create, Present, and Publish your slides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supports speaker notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mobile friendly slides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;controls&#34;&gt;Controls&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next: &lt;code&gt;Right Arrow&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;Space&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Previous: &lt;code&gt;Left Arrow&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start: &lt;code&gt;Home&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish: &lt;code&gt;End&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overview: &lt;code&gt;Esc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaker notes: &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fullscreen: &lt;code&gt;F&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zoom: &lt;code&gt;Alt + Click&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hakimel/reveal.js#pdf-export&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PDF Export&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;code&gt;E&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;code-highlighting&#34;&gt;Code Highlighting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inline code: &lt;code&gt;variable&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code block:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;porridge = &amp;quot;blueberry&amp;quot;
if porridge == &amp;quot;blueberry&amp;quot;:
    print(&amp;quot;Eating...&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;math&#34;&gt;Math&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In-line math: $x + y = z$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Block math:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
f\left( x \right) = ;\frac{{2\left( {x + 4} \right)\left( {x - 4} \right)}}{{\left( {x + 4} \right)\left( {x + 1} \right)}}
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fragments&#34;&gt;Fragments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make content appear incrementally&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;{{% fragment %}} One {{% /fragment %}}
{{% fragment %}} **Two** {{% /fragment %}}
{{% fragment %}} Three {{% /fragment %}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;Space&lt;/code&gt; to play!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;fragment &#34; &gt;
One
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;fragment &#34; &gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Two&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;fragment &#34; &gt;
Three
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fragment can accept two optional parameters:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;class&lt;/code&gt;: use a custom style (requires definition in custom CSS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;weight&lt;/code&gt;: sets the order in which a fragment appears&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;speaker-notes&#34;&gt;Speaker Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add speaker notes to your presentation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-markdown&#34;&gt;{{% speaker_note %}}
- Only the speaker can read these notes
- Press `S` key to view
{{% /speaker_note %}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Press the &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; key to view the speaker notes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only the speaker can read these notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; key to view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;themes&#34;&gt;Themes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;black: Black background, white text, blue links (default)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;white: White background, black text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;league: Gray background, white text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;beige: Beige background, dark text, brown links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sky: Blue background, thin dark text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;night: Black background, thick white text, orange links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;serif: Cappuccino background, gray text, brown links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;simple: White background, black text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;solarized: Cream-colored background, dark green text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;section data-noprocess data-shortcode-slide
  
      
      data-background-image=&#34;/img/boards.jpg&#34;
  &gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;custom-slide&#34;&gt;Custom Slide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customize the slide style and background&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-markdown&#34;&gt;{{&amp;lt; slide background-image=&amp;quot;/img/boards.jpg&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}}
{{&amp;lt; slide background-color=&amp;quot;#0000FF&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}}
{{&amp;lt; slide class=&amp;quot;my-style&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;custom-css-example&#34;&gt;Custom CSS Example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s make headers navy colored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create &lt;code&gt;assets/css/reveal_custom.css&lt;/code&gt; with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-css&#34;&gt;.reveal section h1,
.reveal section h2,
.reveal section h3 {
  color: navy;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://spectrum.chat/academic&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/managing-content/#create-slides&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
