<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Mark Runacres</title>
    <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://mrunacre.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breathney: A modular design toolbox for an affordable ventilator with full functionality</title>
      <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/post/fablab/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrunacre.github.io/post/fablab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Covid-19 pandemic is still progressing globally and a small but significant
fraction of patients need mechanical ventilation at some point. Although some
countries have sufficient ventilators, there are indications of a future global
shortage of such devices. Medtronic released documents for their ventilator,
showing a global urgent need. Rapidly prototyped, industrially manufactured
ventilators can help alleviate this shortage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With crucial support from UZ Brussels , Flanders Make, Audi and other partners,
a team of 40 students, alumni, staff and external experts
at the Fablab Brussels have recently designed and prototyped
a ventilator
that has been produced industrially and is currently being tested extensively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We intend to contribute to the
world-wide ventilator effort in the following way:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perform the scientific experiments to investigate and iteratively increase the
level of compliance with published requirements (e.g.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://tinyurl.com/wfqtk4w&#34;&gt;https://tinyurl.com/wfqtk4w&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demonstrate that a fully functional ventilator can be mass-produced (&amp;gt;100
units daily for a mid-sized facility in e.g. automotive sector) with
minimal pressure on the medical supply chain, by maximally sourcing components
from non-medical sectors, at a well-documented unit cost that is affordable
compared to conventional ventilators (without being low-cost per se)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make available a toolbox for all aspects of ventilator system (mechanical,
electrical, sensors, control, interface). The different aspects are designed
in a modular manner so that e.g. the control unit can be used with both
pump-based and pneumatic approaches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the design open-source. Share the design and documentation. Assist other
groups worldwide in adapting design and setting up local production&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more at 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://breathney.vub.be&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the project&amp;rsquo;s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
