<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>T. De Troyer | Mark Runacres</title>
    <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/authors/t.-de-troyer/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://mrunacre.github.io/authors/t.-de-troyer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>T. De Troyer</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>T. De Troyer</title>
      <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/authors/t.-de-troyer/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Design and manufacturing of a VAWT scale model</title>
      <link>https://mrunacre.github.io/publication/vawt_design/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrunacre.github.io/publication/vawt_design/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper describes the
design, manufacturing and validation of a vertical-axis wind turbine setup for
wind tunnel tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The potential of vertical-axis wind turbines (VAWTs) for specific applications
(floating off-shore or urban in- stallations) has been reconsidered in recent
years. This renewed interest has led to an increasing number of experimental
studies on VAWTs. A challenge of experimental work is correctly interpreting
experimental results but just as important is the design of the experimental
setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objective of the present study is to elaborate on the complete
development process of a VAWT wind tunnel test setup, from design to aerodynamic
interpretation. The effect of the design choices and structural characteristics
of the setup can be traced in the measured torque. The influence of structural
dynamics of an experimental setup are proven to influence unsteady measurements
significantly through the analysis of the spectral content of the measured
torque. An extensive modal analysis of the VAWT rotor allows to link modal
vibrations to their contaminating effect on the measured torque. In addition,
the dynamics of the sensors and setup are found to be important contributions to
the contamination of dynamic measurements. To interpret unsteady torque
measurements, the complete experimental setup needs to be dynamically
characterised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
